In this video, we'll be going over the
next
question about oscillations, and this is a
question
that I really like because it demonstrates
a
lot of what we have learned, not only
oscillations
but also work, and it's a really good
application
of oscillations as well in part b. So,
what
we have here is a simple pendulum consists
of
a small sphere that hangs from a string
with
negligible mass. The top end of the string
is
fixed. The sphere is pulled to point A so
that
the string makes an angle theta, and the
sphere
is released from rest and it oscillates
back
and forth. The work done on the sphere by
Earth
between points A and B is W.
The pendulum is then taken to planet X,
and
the mass of planet X is the same as the
mass
of Earth, but the radius is greater than
the
radius of Earth. So, first of all, when we
see
that the mass of planet X is the same as
the
mass of Earth but the radius is greater,
then
that means that G on planet X will be
smaller
than the acceleration of Earth, because
the
gravitational field strength would be
smaller
for a greater radius. And the sphere is
then
brought back to point A and swung again on
planet
X, and you have to justify why the work
done
on planet X is less than the work done on
planet
E. Well, as I've said in another video, I
don't
remember which one, but I've said this
before,
the work is equal to force times distance.
And also another thing is force times
distance
cosine theta, but also AP Physics 1 has a
formula
booklet, and it basically has everything
you
need to know to solve these questions,
other
than one or two formulae. So what you have
here
is work is equal to force times distance,
or
force times distance in the direction. And
so
it's just mainly about applying these and
understanding
what you're doing. So force, well, force,
Newton's
law, is mass times acceleration.
In this case, it's mass times gravity,
because
that's the acceleration times distance.
And the same thing for X equals
force times distance, and it's equal to
mass
times gravity on X times D, while this is
gravity
times E on D. But like I've explained
before,
since the acceleration on X is lower, so
this
is lower than that, and M and D are
constants
in both cases, because the distance and
the
mass of the ball are the same, then we can
conclude
that the work done on X is less than the
work
done on E, and that's basically what you
need
to explain. I'm not going to write it
down,
but the question is solved.
You just need to state what I've said.
Okay,
a new pendulum is made by hanging the same
small
sphere on a different string with
negligible
mass. Different string means that the
length
of the string is different. The new string
is
slightly elastic, and the length of the
string
may increase or decrease depending on the
tension
applied. I haven't read this question in a
while,
but from what I see here, you don't really
need
to mind this. All you need to know is that
the
length of the string can vary. On Earth,
when
the sphere is displaced from the vertical
and
released from rest, the new pendulum
oscillates
with this period. And then the new
pendulum
is taken to a different planet with the
same
radius, but a larger mass.
So basically, that means a larger G.
So G of Y is bigger than G of E.
And on planet Y, it oscillates with period
T
Y. And you have to explain how T Y could
be
larger than T, or it could also be smaller
than
T. Now, I'm not going to write a
paragraph,
but I'm going to explain why. So
basically,
first of all, when we do this, we want to
know
our variables in play. And I would be
pulling
up the formula sheet if I was doing the
exam
right now. And you would know that T P
equals
2 pi root L over G, as we've learned.
So T equals 2 pi root L
over G. Now, it's kind of obvious now
why it could be either larger or smaller.
If the length of the string is
way, way larger, then the period on Earth
would
be greater. So if it's elastic, if it's
more
elastic, then the period on Earth could be
greater.
But, sorry, the period on planet Y could
be
greater. Because if it's more elastic,
then
the length on planet Y would be larger,
because
there would be a greater tension force.
But if it's not so elastic, that means
that
gravity on planet Y would be way, way
larger
than the gravity on planet E or Earth.
So if it's not so elastic, then the
period on planet Y would be less.
And the period on planet E would be
greater.
So it really depends on the elasticity of
the
string. And that's basically how you
answer
the question. So say that gravity is
inversely
related to period. So if gravity is
greater,
then the period will be smaller. And also
say
that length is related, or the root of
length
is related to period. So if it's really
elastic,
which means the length will be greater,
then
the period on planet Y would be greater,
because
it would have a larger length. Since it's
elastic,
and planet Y's greater gravitational field
would
pull it down more, and result in more
elasticity
and more length. And that's basically how
you
answer this question. Okay, that's all for
today's
video, and I hope you enjoyed.
Thank you!